Guide to the James L. Weil Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James L. Weil papers
1927-2005
YCAL MSS 825
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
15.45
(27 boxes)
The Weil papers contain correspondence, production files and writings, records of the Elizabeth Press, printed and audiovisual materials, and personal papers. The collection is made up of twenty-one separate donations made by Weil from 1983 to 2005. The first several accessions consist exclusively of materials relating to publications by Weil, while later accessions, beginning with the October 1990 Acquisition, consist of larger groups of material including correspondence, production files, and other papers. Correspondence in the collection, which features letters from writers, journal editors, publishers, booksellers, the many libraries to which Weil made donations, and others, is thus spread over multiple accessions. It is either sorted roughly, into so-called letter general folders ("A"-"Z") or by date, or it is unsorted; the bulk of the letters are also still housed in original envelopes. Individual correspondents include: Bob Arnold of Longhouse Publishers & Booksellers, Cid Corman, Theodore Enslin, David Giannini, Lyman Gilmore, Henry Lyman, Simon Perchik, Felix Stefanile, Jack Stillinger, Pierre Ullman, and others. Correspondence can include enclosures, such as drafts of writings, photographs, and printed material. Most of the production files in the collection appear to relate to the limited edition chapbooks and printed keepsakes published by Weil under his own name (James L. Weil, Publisher) from the mid 1980s onward, though records relating to the Elizabeth Press (1963-1981) can also be found. The production files, which include correspondence, drafts, specifications, proofs, and printed versions, feature work by William Bronk, Cid Corman, Larry Eigner, Aleksis Rannit, Karl Shapiro, Felix Stefanile, and others. Printed materials include newspapers, journals, clippings, and offprints containing reviews and concerning literary matters such as modern fine printing and small press publishing.
Weil, James L., 1929-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of James L. Weil, 1983-2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Boxes 5 and 9 (reel-to-reel tapes): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Boxes 6 and 25 (audio and video cassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
James L. Weil (1929-2006)
James L. Weil, born 15 June 1929 in New York to Morris, a financier, and Charlotte (Ullman) Weil, was a poet and publisher. He attended the University of Chicago (1950) and Oxford University (1954) before going to work for the Dialight Corporation (1954-1968). Weil founded the Elizabeth Press (1963-1981), an important publisher of American poetry in the 1960s and 1970s, and published limited edition chapbooks and keepsakes under his own name from 1985 onward. His authors include William Bronk (1918-1999), Cid Corman (1924-2004), Larry Eigner (1927-1996), Theodore Enslin (1925-2011), Felix Stefanile (1920-2009), and others.
Scope and Contents
The James L. Weil papers contain correspondence, production files and writings, records of the Elizabeth Press, printed and audiovisual materials, and personal papers. The collection is made up of twenty-one separate donations made by Weil from 1983 to 2005. The first several accessions consist exclusively of materials relating to publications by Weil, while later accessions, beginning with the October 1990 Acquisition, consist of larger groups of material including correspondence, production files, and other papers. Correspondence in the collection, which features letters from writers, journal editors, publishers, booksellers, the many libraries to which Weil made donations, and others, is thus spread over multiple accessions. It is either sorted roughly, into so-called letter general folders ("A" - "Z") or by date, or it is unsorted; the bulk of the letters are also still housed in original envelopes. Individual correspondents include: Bob Arnold of Longhouse Publishers & Booksellers, Cid Corman, Theodore Enslin, David Giannini, Lyman Gilmore, Henry Lyman, Simon Perchik, Felix Stefanile, Jack Stillinger, Pierre Ullman, and others. Correspondence can include enclosures, such as drafts of writings, photographs, and printed material. Most of the production files in the collection appear to relate to the limited edition chapbooks and printed keepsakes published by Weil under his own name (James L. Weil, Publisher) from the mid 1980s onward, though records relating to the Elizabeth Press (1963-1981) can also be found. The production files, which include correspondence, drafts, specifications, proofs, and printed versions, feature work by William Bronk, Cid Corman, Larry Eigner, Aleksis Rannit, Karl Shapiro, Felix Stefanile, and others. Printed materials include newspapers, journals, clippings, and offprints containing reviews and concerning literary matters such as modern fine printing and small press publishing.
Arrangement
Organized into twenty-one groupings: January 1983 Acquisition, April 1984 Acquisition, October 1984 Acquisition, February 1985 Acquisition, October 1985 Acquisition, January 1986 Acquisition, September 1986 Acquisition, January 1987 Acquisition, December 1987 Acquisition, June 1989 Acquisition, October 1990 Acquisition, January 1992 Acquisition, March 1993 Acquisition, December 1994 Acquisition, July 1997 Acquisition, April 1998 Acquisition, May 1998 Acquisition, February 2000 Acquisition, January 2002 Acquisition, May 2005 Acquisition, and September 2005 Acquisition.
American literature -- 20th Century; Fine books -- United States; Poets, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Publishers and publishing -- United States; Small presses -- United States; Audiovisual materials; Photographic prints; Sound recordings; Poets -- United States -- 20th Century; Arnold, Bob, 1952-; Bronk, William, 1918-1999; Corman, Cid, 1924-; Eigner, Larry, 1927-1996; Enslin, Theodore, 1925-; Giannini, David, 1948-; Gilmore, Lyman, 1933-; Lyman, Henry, 1942-; Perchik, Simon, 1923-; Rannit, Aleksis; Shapiro, Karl, 1913-2000; Stefanile, Felix, 1920-; Stillinger, Jack; Ullman, Pierre L., 1929-; Weil, James L., 1929-; Elizabeth Press; James L. Weil (Publisher); Longhouse (Firm)
- January 1983 Acquisition, 1982-1983
  Immediate Source of Acquisition
  Gift of James Weil, 1983.
  Scope and Contents
  The January 1983 Acquisition consists of drafts, proofs, and other materials relating to publication of As David Danced by William Bronk.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms Weil.
  - As David Danced, drafts, autograph manuscript and typescript, and proofs, 1982-1983 (Box 1)
- April 1984 Acquisition, 1983-1984; 2
  Gift of James Weil, 1984.
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically by title.
  The April 1984 Acquisition contains correspondence relating to As David Danced and various materials, including drafts and proofs, relating to publication of A Happiness In Shops by John Synge.
  - As David Danced, correspondence, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - A Happiness In Shops, draft, proofs, and printed version, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- October 1984 Acquisition, 1983-1984
  The October 1984 Acquisition contains various materials, including correspondence, drafts, proofs, and a printed version, relating to publication of Some People Think by James Laughlin.
  - Some People Think, correspondence, drafts, proofs, and printed version, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- February 1985 Acquisition, 1983
  Gift of James Weil, 1985.
  The February 1985 Acquisition contains drafts of Equinox and other poems by William Bronk and other publication material relating to Equinox.
  - Equinox, draft, typescript, proof, and printed version, 1983, undated (Box 1)
- October 1985 Acquisition, 1983-1985
  The October 1985 Acquisition contains material relating to editions of "To My Brother George" by John Keats.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 338.
  - To My Brother George, correspondence, proofs, and other material, 1983-1985 (Box 1)
- January 1986 Acquisition, 1983-1985; 9
  Gift of James Weil, 1986.
  Arranged alphabetically by name.
  The January 1986 Acquisition consists of production files for publications of work by William Bronk, Larry Eigner, John Keats, John Pearlman, and Felix Stefanile. Materials include correspondence, research material, drafts, and page proofs.
  - Bronk, William, 1984, undated (Box 1)
  - Eigner, Larry, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
  - Keats, John, 1983-1985, undated; 6 (Box 1)
  - Perlman, John, 1984 (Box 1)
  - Stefanile, Felix, 1983-1984 (Box 1)
- September 1986 Acquisition, 1985; 2
  The September 1986 Acquisition consists of publication material relating to William Bronk's Holy Orders and The Untold.
  - Holy Orders, correspondence, draft, and proofs, 1985, undated (Box 1)
  - The Untold, correspondence, draft, and proofs, 1985, undated (Box 1)
- January 1987 Acquisition, 1984; 4
  Gift of James Weil, 1987.
  The January 1987 Acquisition contains production files for George Spelvin by Spencer Brown and The Life and Winter Evening by William Bronk.
  - George Spelvin, correspondence, drafts, corrected, and proof, 1984 (Box 1)
  - The Life, proofs, undated (Box 1)
  - Winter Evening, proofs, undated (Box 1)
  - Empty envelopes, undated (Box 1)
- December 1987 Acquisition, 1984-1987; 0.42; (1 box)
  The December 1987 Acquisition contains production files, including correspondence, drafts, publisher's specifications, and proofs, relating to fifteen chapbooks and keepsakes issued by Weil during the mid 1980s.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 339.
  - All My Life, correspondence, drafts, proofs, and printed version, 1984-1985, undated (Box 2)
  - Apud libros, proof and printed version, undated (Box 2)
  - Dawnings, proof and printed version, 1987 (Box 2)
  - For Jim, proofs and printed version, 1986 (Box 2)
  - Four Sonnets By Four Friends, correspondence, drafts, proofs and printed version, 1985-1987 (Box 2)
  - Keats and Me, correspondence, specifications, proofs, and printed version, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Keats on Board, correspondence, drawings, proofs, and printed version, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - Letter To a Young Poet, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1986, undated (Box 2)
  - Letter To Felix, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1984-1985 (Box 2)
  - On Reading Keats In War Time, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1986 (Box 2)
  - On the Living Poets, proof and printed version, undated (Box 2)
  - A Room In Rome, correspondence, specifications, proofs, and printed version, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Some Token of, correspondence, draft, proof, and printed version, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Two Poems To Two Prints, correspondence, drafts, and printed version, 1987, undated (Box 2)
  - What Art Is, correspondence, proof, and printed version, 1986-1987 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence with Jack Stillinger (photocopies), 1984-1987 (Box 2)
- June 1989 Acquisition, 1986-1989; 0.21; (1 box)
  Gift of James Weil, 1989.
  The June 1989 Acquisition consists of additional production files for publications by Weil.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 107.
  - Adversaries, correspondence, proof, and printed version, 1988 (Box 3)
  - The Alphabet, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - Arts of the Book, draft, mock-up, and printed version, 1988 (Box 3)
  - I Want My Music Bent, correspondence, proof, and printed version, 1989 (Box 3)
  - Jacque's Geometry, correspondence, drafts, and printed version, 1986-1988 (Box 3)
  - Of Poetry, correspondence, manuscript notes, proofs, and printed versions, 1988; 2 (Box 3)
  - On the Lookout For a Poet, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1988-1989 (Box 3)
  - To George Felton Mathew, printed version, proofs, and printed version, 1988 (Box 3)
- October 1990 Acquisition, 1955-1990; 0.84; (3 boxes)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Box 5 (audiotape reels): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Box 6 (audiocassettes): Use of originals is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Gift of James Weil, 1990.
  Organized into four subgroupings: Correspondence, Production Files, Sound Recordings, and Other Papers.
  The October 1990 Acquisition contains correspondence, production files for printed keepsakes and chapbooks, sound recordings of Weil and others, and other papers.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 152.
  - Correspondence
    - The Elizabeth Press, circa 1960-1980 (Box 4)
    - Poetry, 1965-1969, undated (Box 4)
    - Unsorted correspondence, 1955-1990; 4 (Box 4)
  - Production Files
    - Adonais, correspondence, proof, and printed version, 1990 (Box 4)
    - Bedrock and Stones, proofs and printed version, undated (Box 4)
    - Beethoven: The Late Sonatas, draft, proofs, and printed version, 1990 (Box 4)
    - To Answer Robert Frost, correspondence, draft, proof, and printed version, 1988-1989 (Box 4)
    - To Charles Cowden Clarke, proofs and printed version, undated (Box 4)
    - Your Poems, drafts, proof, and printed version, 1990 (Box 4)
  - Sound Recordings
    Audiovisual material. Restricted fragile. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - "James Weil...single track @ 7.5/sec" (1 of 2), 1979 October 24; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002104618054)
    - "James Weil...single track @ 7.5/sec" (2 of 2), 1979 October 24; 1 (Box 5, Item barcode 39002104618062)
    - "Gogisgi / Carroll Arnett. Reading at Knox", undated; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002104617999)
      A list of contents is included with the tape.
      The Story of My Life
      Land
      Removal
      Anadarko John
      Found in Mecosta
      Out in the Woods
      Now This
      Seven Medicine Songs
      Tlanuwa
      Nine Raccoons
      Homage to Andrew Jackson
      Roadman
      The Old Man Said
      Mecosta County Police Officers Association Speaking
      Powwow
      At White Earth
      Hayward
      "That'll Be the Day"
      Early Song
    - "Larry Eigner", undated; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002104618005)
    - "Martin Booth", undated; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002104618013)
    - Perchik, Enslin, Williams, 1965 January-November; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002104618021)
    - "Weil Interview/JKO, New Rochelle, N.Y.", 1976 July 2; 1 (Box 6, Item barcode 39002104618039)
  - Other Papers
    - Copyrights, circa 1962-1980 (Box 4)
    - Notes, undated (Box 4)
    - Saturday Review, 1968 January 20 (Box 4)
- January 1992 Acquisition, 1949-1991; 0.84; (3 boxes)
  Box 9 (audiotape reel): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
  Gift of James Weil, 1992.
  Organized into three subgroupings: Correspondence, Production Files, and Other Material.
  The January 1992 Acquisition includes correspondence, production files, and other material. Correspondence consists of letters to James Weil from writers, journal editors, publishers, booksellers, libraries, acknowledging gifts, and others, dating predominantly from 1990 and 1991, with one large file for Jack Stillinger. Production files include several folders for additional chapbooks by William Bronk and others. Other materials includes an audio tape of James Weil reading at the Library of Congress.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 242.
  - Correspondence
    - "A" - "S" general, 1949-1991, undated; 16 (Box 7)
    - Stillinger, Jack, 1984-1991; 2 (Box 7)
    - "T" - "Z" general, 1990-1991; 4 (Box 7)
    - Unidentified, 1988-1991; 4 (Box 7)
  - Production Files
    - Dear Reynolds, as last night I lay in bed, correspondence, research material, proofs, and printed version, 1985-1991 (Box 8)
    - Formal Declaration, correspondence, specifications, proofs, and printed version, 1989-1991 (Box 8)
    - Formalities, drafts, specifications, proofs, and printed version, 1989-1990 (Box 8)
    - Lovely Lessons, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Sizes, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1991 (Box 8)
    - Something Given, correspondence, proofs, and printed version, 1990-1991 (Box 8)
  - Other Material
    - "James L. Weil Reading at the Library of Congress..." (reel-to-reel tape), 1979 October 24
    - Miscellaneous material, 1988-1989, undated (Box 8)
  - Restricted Fragile Material
    Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
    - Weil reading at the Library of Congress (2 of 2), 1979 October 24; 1 (Box 9, Item barcode 39002104618047)
- March 1993 Acquisition, 1952-1993; 1.46; (4 boxes)
  Gift of James Weil, 1993.
  Organized into four subgroupings: Correspondence, Production Files and Writings, Elizabeth Press Records, and Printed Material.
  The March 1993 Acquisition consists of correspondence, production files and writings, records of the Elizabeth Press, and printed and other material. Correspondence again features letters to Weil from writers, journal editors, publishers, booksellers, libraries, and others. Correspondence dates heavily from 1992, but there is some early personal correspondence and, in addition to incoming letters, there are scattered photocopies of outgoing letters from Weil to others. Production files include folders for work by William Bronk, Aleksis Rannit, and others, as well as proofs for Weil's Something Given: Very Selected Poems, 1964-1991 (1992). Printed materials include newspapers, journals, clippings, and offprints containing reviews and discussing literary matters such as modern fine printing and small press publishing.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 274.
  - Correspondence
    - "A" - "Z" general, 1952-1993, undated; 17 (Box 10)
      Includes photographs
  - Production Files and Writings
    - Acts of Devotion by William Bronk, 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - All Together Now by William Bronk, 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - The Grasshopper and the Cricket: 30 December 1816 (texts by Charles Cowden Clarke, Leigh Hunt, John Keats, and Richard Woodhouse), 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - The Laurel Crown: December 1816-March 1817 (texts by Leigh Hunt, John Keats, and Richard Woodhouse), 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - The Nile: 4 February 1818 (texts by Leigh Hunt, John Keats, Percy Bysshe Shelley, and Richard Woodhouse), 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - Ozymandias by Percy Bysshe Shelley, 1992, undated (Box 11)
    - "Shelley posters", 1991-1992, undated (Box 11)
    - Something Given by James L. Weil, 1992, undated; 5 (Box 11)
    - Stones of Estonia by Alexis Rannit, 1992, undated; 2 (Box 11)
    - Stones of Estonia by Alexis Rannit, 1992, undated; 6 (Box 12)
    - What Keats Looked Like by James L. Weil, 1992, undated (Box 12)
  - Elizabeth Press Records
    - Financial records, 1971-1984, undated; 4 (Box 12)
    - Publicity, 1964-1979, undated (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous material, undated (Box 12)
  - Printed Material
    - Printed material, 1962-1992, undated; 9 (Box 13)
- December 1994 Acquisition, 1984-1994; 1; (1 box)
  Gift of James Weil, 1994.
  Organized into three subgroupings: Correspondence, Production Files, and Other Papers.
  The December 1994 Acquisition contains correspondence, production files for work by William Bronk, Richard Woodhouse, and others, and unsorted material. Correspondence, arranged in chonological order by month, dates predominantly from January 1992 through December 1994.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 418.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, 1984-1994, undated; 42 (Box 14)
  - Production Files
    - Bare Bones by William Bronk, 1990-1994 (Box 14)
    - "Basalt touchstone from Staff...", 1993, undated (Box 14)
    - "Bill's Shaker Chair", 1993 (Box 14)
    - Exemplaires by William Bronk, 1994 (Box 14)
    - Notes on Notices by Richard Woodhouse, 1993, undated (Box 14)
    - The Shaker Chair by William Bronk, 1993, undated (Box 14)
    - "Westchester Walls", 1994 (Box 14)
  - Other Papers
    - Miscellaneous material, 1984-1993, undated; 2 (Box 14)
- July 1997 Acquisition, 1960-1997; 2.42; (3 boxes)
  Gift of James Weil, 1995.
  Organized into three subgroupings: Correspondence, Production Files and Writings, and Other Papers.
  The July 1997 Acquisition contains correspondence, production files and writings, and other papers, including printed material relating to the Elizabeth Press.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 535.
  - Correspondence
    - Correspondence, [circa 1960-1997]; 16 (Box 15)
    - Correspondence, [circa 1960-1997; 8 (Box 16)
  - Production Files and Writings
    - As Gods Go by James L. Weil, 1996 (Box 16)
    - Bill's Shaker Chair by James L. Weil, 1995 (Box 16)
    - The Choice of Words by William Bronk, 1995 (Box 16)
    - Flanders Field 1914/1996 by James L. Weil, 1997, undated (Box 16)
    - From the Life: John Severn to John Taylor, 1995-1997 (Box 16)
    - In Private by William Bronk, 1996 (Box 16)
    - Lite by William Bronk, 1994-1995 (Box 16)
    - Missing Persons by William Bronk, 1995-1996 (Box 16)
    - Shelley, 1997, undated (Box 16)
    - Ten Sonnets by John Keats, 1994-1995; 2 (Box 16)
    - To Ailsa Rock by John Keats, 1993, undated (Box 16)
    - Unsorted writings, 1996, undated; 2 (Box 16)
  - Other Papers
    - "Book Reviews" (clippings), circa 1960s-1980s; 5 (Box 16)
    - "Book Reviews" (clippings), circa 1960s-1980s; 5 (Box 17)
    - Button, undated (Box 17)
    - Passport, 1987-1997 (Box 17)
    - Printed material, 1973-1997; 5 (Box 17)
- April 1998 Acquisition, 1927-1980s; 0.63; (2 boxes)
  Gift of James Weil, 1998.
  Organized into two subgroupings: Writings by Spencer Brown and Other Material Relating to Spencer Brown.
  The April 1998 Acquisition consists of articles and collections of poems by Spencer Brown, arranged alphabetically, along with unsorted material relating to Brown.
  Former call number: Uncat Za Ms 557.
  - Writings by Spencer Brown
    - "Anxiety and Education: The Crisis in College Admissions," draft, typescript, circa 1960 (Box 18)
    - "Arthur Koestler," printed version, American Mercury, 1952 October (Box 18)
    - "Between Journalism and the Essay," printed version, Sewanee Review, 1981 (Box 18)
    - "The Bible and a Liberal Education," printed version, Commentary, 1953 October (Box 18)
    - "A Code of Honor for a Mutinous Era," printed version, Commentary, 1952 June (Box 18)
    - "Collected Poems," drafts, typescript, undated; 3 (Box 18)
    - "The Ethics of Soviet Apology," draft, typescript, circa 1951 (Box 18)
    - "Five Women Critics," printed version, Sewanee Review, 1984 (Box 18)
    - "A Fortnight in Iceland," draft, typescript, 1979 (Box 18)
    - "A Gentile Looks at the Jews," draft, typescript, circa 1962 (Box 18)
    - "The Habits of Toms and Tabbies in Captivity," draft, typescript, 1938 November 3 (Box 18)
    - "The Hot War Over Our Schools," printed version, Commentary, 1954 March (Box 18)
    - " Huckleberry Finn for our Time," printed versions, Michigan Quarterly, 1967 January (Box 18)
    - "Hunters Unlimited," printed version, Harper's Magazine, 1975 May (Box 18)
    - "Ibsen Reconsidered," printed version, Sewanee Review, 1980 (Box 18)
    - "Late Autumn of the 'Liberal Drama'," printed version, Commentary, 1954 December (Box 18)
    - "My Father's Business and Other Poems," drafts, typescript, circa 1951-1956 (Box 18)
    - "My World Series," draft, typescript, and printed version, Sports Illustrated, 1962 October 1 (Box 18)
    - "The Poetry of Edwin Arlington Robinson," draft, typescript, 1927 October (Box 18)
    - "The Rhetoric of 'Dissent'," draft, typescript, circa 1955 (Box 18)
    - "T. S. Eliot's Latest Poetic Drama," printed version (photocopy), Commentary, 1954 April (Box 18)